Guide to the Eloise Ellery Papers, 1870-1959 (bulk 1923-1958)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Eloise Ellery Papers
1870-1959
1923-1958
Ellery, Eloise, 1874-1958
3.4 cubic feet (1200 items in 17 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Correspondence, diaries, manuscripts and typescripts, newspaper clippings, travel documents, legal and financial papers, family papers, photographs, printed materials and miscellaneous items relating to the life and work of Eloise Ellery. There is also significant collection of items which belonged to Frank Ellery.
Biographical Note
Born in Rochester, NY in 1874, Eloise Ellery (1874 - 1958) was the only child of Frank M. and Mary Alida Alling Ellery. Frank Ellery was a rising member of the Rochester business community. He became Secretary and later trustee of the Security Trust Company in Rochester. Miss Ellery attended the Rochester Free Academy and entered Vassar College as a freshman in 1893. A history student under the tutelage of Vassar's own Lucy Maynard Salmon, Miss Ellery graduated Phi Beta Kappa from Vassar in 1897. That was the beginning of an association which would span her lifetime. Upon graduation from Vassar, she went to Cornell as a Babbott Fellow to do graduate work in history and political science. Fellowships from Vassar, Cornell, and the Association of Collegiate Alumnae allowed Miss Ellery to study at the Sorbonne and do research at the Bibliotheque Nationale from 1899 to 1900. Returning to Vassar in 1900 as an assistant in history, Miss Ellery long remained a vital force in the History Department as well as the College. In 1916, she became a full professor, was department chairman from 1923 to 1932 and retired in 1939 as professor emeritus of history. She served as Secretary of the Faculty from 1910 to 1923.
Miss Ellery traveled extensively -- most notable was a trip taken in 1923-1924. On leave from Vassar, she traveled around the world with her father. Stopping in Shanghai, China to visit a former student, Sophia Chen Zen, '19, Miss Ellery met with prominent leaders of Young China. A typescript written by Zen and included within the Collection records the highlights of this visit.
A vigorous scholar and experienced traveler, Miss Ellery made for a devoted teacher who demanded top quality work from every student. For many years, Miss Ellery taught Renaissance and Reformation, French Revolution and Contemporary Western Europe as a three year-long course. Writing about Ellery's teaching, Helen D. Lockwood, a student and later colleague of Miss Ellery's, wrote "E.E. drew out and expected to be expressed with thoroughness and polish the would capacity of every student whether the specially able and gifted, the sensitive, problem student or the ordinary run."
Innovative in her teaching methods and a devotee of Miss Salmon's philosophy of using primary source materials, Miss Ellery required of all her students a long paper to be done over the whole term. Out of this exercise, Lockwood wrote, "…came the profound inner change in a student's thinking, the toughness and delight of intellectual adventure...."
In a letter to Frank Ellery, Vassar's President MacCracken also spoke of Miss Ellery's teaching: "There is no one among the whole one hundred and twenty-five [faculty] who seems to have the ability to lift students up to the best that is in them and keep them steadily and enthusiastically at work as does your daughter..."
Yet devotion to her students did not end upon their graduation from Vassar. Amusing and constant, Miss Ellery took her role as correspondent seriously. She oftentimes labored over letters, keeping them informative but at the same time safe from censors. Evidence of this can be found in correspondence form Ilse Hecht '29, a former student teaching in East Germany, Sophia Chen Zen '19, teaching in China, and Irene Mott '22, the wife of a High Court judge living in Nagpur, India. She also wrote frequently to Rebecca L. Lowrie '13, a close personal friend and trustee of Vassar.
Outside of teaching, Miss Ellery served as an associate on the staff of Current History from 1921 to 1931, reporting monthly on political developments in Italy, Spain and Portugal. She also wrote many articles for the American Historical Review. Her one book was published in 1915 in a series commemorating Vassar's 50th Anniversary. Expanding her doctoral dissertation into a full-length biography, Miss Ellery published an authoritive work. Brissot de Warville, A Study in the History of the French Revolution was called by one reviewer "the only biography in existence of the Chief of the Girondin party in the French Revolution."
Upon her retirement in 1939, Miss Ellery went to Washington, D.C. for a year to study Spanish literature and to follow Congressional matters. She returned to Poughkeepsie in 1940, and remained a familiar and striking figure on campus until her death in July 1958. She was 84.
In October, 1958, as part of the College's $25,000,000 Development Program, the Eloise Ellery Chair of History was established. The Chair memorialized "her outstanding service to the College as a teacher, scholar and benefactor."
For more biographical information see:
Barbour, Violet. "Memorandum on Professor Eloise Ellery," 1958.
Lockwood, Helen D. "Some Notes on E.E.'s Teaching," 1958
Scope and Content Note
Correspondence, diaries, manuscripts and typescripts, newspaper clippings, travel documents, legal and financial papers, family papers, photographs, printed materials and miscellaneous items relating to the life and work of Eloise Ellery. There is also significant collection of items which belonged to Frank Ellery.
Correspondence is the largest portion of the papers and consists primarily of letters received from her father Frank Ellery, 1891-1929; from Ilse Hecht on teaching in East Germany, 1947-1957; from Rebecca L. Lowrie, friend and Vassar colleague, about personal and professional issues, 1936-1956; from Irene Mott, wife of a High Court Judge in India, about political situations there, Indian people, and World War II, 1924-1951; from C. Mildred Thompson, friend, colleague, and former Dean of the College, about teaching duties, an education conference in London (1944), professional and social life at the University of Georgia, and teaching in Europe, 1941-1952. There is also correspondence regarding the estate of Mary Frazer, family affairs, and other matters, 1929-1958; as well as a few family and personal letters by Ellery, 1899-1957.
Ellery's diaries include records of daily activities, 1940-1957, health records, 1953-1955, reading and quotation journal, 1919-1956, and grade books, 1926-1939. Manuscripts and printed materials include an account of Ellery's trip to China, 1923-1924, by her former student Sophia Chen Zen; her published articles, 1928-1929; and articles and clippings about Ellery and her father, Frank Ellery, 1897-1929, and his diaries for 1910-1929; and estate papers, receipts, and inventories for Abby M. Alling, Eloise Ellery, and Mary Frazer, 1929-1958.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
The Lucy Maynard Salmon and Helen D. Lockwood Collections—both housed in Vassar's Special Collection—contain substantial correspondence between Miss Ellery and these two friends and colleagues.
Subject Headings
Names:
Ch'en, Heng-che, 1890-1976; Ellery, Frank; Hecht, Ilse, 1907-; Lowrie, Rebecca Lawrence, 1891-1975; Mott, Irene; Thompson, C. Mildred (Clara Mildred), 1881-1975; Frazer, Mary; Alling, Abby M.
Organizations:
Vassar College--Faculty; University of Georgia
Subjects:
Women--Diaries; Education--Germany (East); Education--Europe; Decedents' estates; World War, 1939-1945; Women college teachers
Places:
India--Politics and government; India--Description and travel; Germany (East)--Description and travel; China--Description and travel; Europe--Description and travel
Document Types:
Diaries; Photographs
VCL Categories
Education; Travel; Vassar College
Encoding Information
Encoded by Elizabeth Clarke, March 2007.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the estate of Eloise Ellery and from Helen D. Lockwood, 1958.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in 9 series. Whenever possible all letters have been dated. Undated letters or fragments from a known correspondent are placed at the end of that file. All unidentified correspondence is at the end of the Correspondence series. Frank Ellery's materials have not been separated, but rather have been placed at the end of the appropriate series.
Series List
- Series I. Correspondence, (Boxes 1-4)
  Personal Correspondence to Eloise Ellery
  Personal Correspondence from Eloise Ellery
  Financial and Legal Correspondence to Eloise Ellery
  Financial and Legal Correspondence from Eloise Ellery
  Correspondence about Eloise Ellery by Others
  Frank M. Ellery Correspondence
  Miscellaneous
- Series II. Manuscripts and Typescripts, (Box 5)
  Unpublished Material
  Published Material
- Series III. Printed Materials, (Boxes 5-7)
  Addresses and Announcements
  Articles Written by Eloise Ellery
  Articles Written about Eloise Ellery
  Booklets
  Newspaper Clippings
- Series IV. Personal Commonplace Books, (Boxes 8-15)
  Eloise Ellery's Daily Diaries
  Record Books and Notes
  Frank M. Ellery's Daily Diaries
- Series V. Legal Documents, (Box 16 and Folder 139, drawer 36 mapcase)
  Travel Documents
  Letter of Introduction
  Library Cards
  Estates
  Oversized
- Series VI. Financial Documents, (Box 17)
- Series VII. The Ellery Family, (Box 17)
- Series VIII. Photographs, (Box 17)
- Series IX. Fragments, (Box 17)
Container List
- SERIES I. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Personal Correspondence to Eloise Ellery
    - Ellery, Frank M., 1891-1928; (25 letters, 1 w/ Xerox) (Folder 1.1)
    - Ellery, Frank M., 1929; (1 poem - 2MS, 2 Xerox) (Folder 1.2)
    - Hecht, Ilse, 1947-1952; (13 letters) (Folder 1.3)
    - Hecht, Ilse, 1953; (9 letters) (Folder 1.4)
    - Hecht, Ilse, 1954-1957; (10 letters, 1 postcard) (Folder 1.5)
    - Lowrie, Rebecca, 1936-1951; (15 letters) (Folder 1.6)
    - Lowrie, Rebecca, 1952-1953; (20 letters) (Folder 1.7)
    - Lowrie, Rebecca, 1954; (19 letters) (Folder 1.8)
    - Lowrie, Rebecca, 1955-1956, n.d.; (10 letters) (Folder 1.9)
    - Lowrie, Rebecca I, n.d.; (5 Christmas cards) (Folder 1.10)
    - Lowrie, Rebecca II, n.d.; (5 Christmas cards, 1 tea mat) (Folder 1.11)
    - Mott, Irene, 1924-1939; (3 letters, 1 Typescript) (Folder 1.12)
    - Mott, Irene, 1942-1951, n.d.; (4 letters, 1 Christmas card, with pictures) (Folder 2.13)
    - Otley, Roberta, 1939-1958; (7 letters, 1 note) (Folder 2.14)
    - Thompson, C. Mildred, 1941-1950; (13 letters, 1 postcard) (Folder 2.15)
    - Thompson, C. Mildred, 1952; (6 letters, 2 postcards, 2 c.c.) (Folder 2.16)
    - Thompson, C. Mildred, 1953-1954; (16 letters, 1 postcard) (Folder 2.17)
    - Thompson, C. Mildred, 1955; (12 letters, 2 postcards, 1 c.c.) (Folder 2.18)
    - Thompson, C. Mildred, 1956-1957, n.d.; (15 letters, 1 postcard, fragments) (Folder 2.19)
    - "Miss A"- Benet, 1952-1957, n.d.; (8 letters, 9 postcards) (Folder 2.20)
    - Blanding-Canda, 1946-1956, n.d.; (12 letters, 4 cards, 3 postcards) (Folder 2.21)
    - Clifford-Elsworth, 1951-1957, n.d.; (15 letters, 4 cards, 1 postcard) (Folder 3.22)
    - Foster-McClelland, 1939-1958, n.d.; (9 letters, 6 cards, 6 postcards) (Folder 3.23)
    - McKnight-Rapin, 1951-1958, n.d.; (12 letters) (Folder 3.24)
    - Reed-Zen, 1940-1957, n.d.; (9 letters, 4 cards, 3 postcards) (Folder 3.25)
    - Other Family correspondents, 1933-1956, n.d.; (9 letters, 3 cards, 2 xeroxed telegrams, 4 announcements) (Folder 3.26)
  - Personal Correspondence from Eloise Ellery
    - Mother and Father, 1899; (1 letter) (Folder 3.27)
    - Frank M. Ellery, 1957; (3 letters) (Folder 3.28)
    - Others, 1903-1957; (16 letters, 2 postcards) (Folder 3.29)
  - Financial and Legal Correspondence to Eloise Ellery
    - Letters of receipt from Vassar College, 1933-1940; (12 letters, xerox) (Folder 3.30)
    - Letters re: Salary and Pension, 1929-1939; (7 letters) (Folder 3.31)
    - Letters re: Frazer Estate, 1935-1944; (9 letters) (Folder 4.32)
    - Other financial and legal correspondence, 1933-1954; (5 letters) (Folder 4.33)
    - Other professional correspondence, 1939-1956, n.d.; (10 letters) (Folder 4.34)
  - Financial and Legal Correspondence from Eloise Ellery
    - Letters re: Frazer Estate, 1934-1944; (3 letters, 4 c.c.) (Folder 4.35)
    - Other professional correspondence, 1933-1954, n.d.; (6 letters, 3 c.c.) (Folder 4.36)
  - Correspondence about Eloise Ellery by Others
    - Letters to Dr. Jane Baldwin, 1958; (4 letters) (Folder 4.37)
    - Letters to Helen D. Lockwood, 1958-1959; (11 letters, 1 c.c.) (Folder 4.38)
    - Letters by Helen D. Lockwood, 1958; (11 letters, 1 note) (Folder 4.39)
    - Other correspondence about Eloise Ellery by others, 1946-1958; (7 letters) (Folder 4.40)
  - Frank M. Ellery Correspondence
    - Letters to Frank Ellery by other than Eloise, 1925-1929; (5 letters - 1 with copy, 1 with Xerox) (Folder 4.41)
    - Letters by Frank Ellery to other than Eloise, 1897-1924; (3 letters) (Folder 4.42)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Fragments or unidentified letters, n.d.; (1 letter, 3 cards, 3 postcards, 1 envelope) (Folder 4.43)
- SERIES II. MANUSCRIPTS AND TYPESCRIPTS
  - Unpublished Material
    - Barbour, Violet. "Memorandum on Professor Eloise Ellery,", 1958; (10 page TS and draft) (Folder 5.44)
    - Hecht, Ilse, April 20, 1940; (TS, 6 pages) (Folder 5.45)
    - VC History Department. "Memorial minute,", Oct. 6, 1958; (TS, 4 pages) (Folder 5.46)
    - Lockwood, Helen D. "Some notes on E.E.'s Teaching,", August 28, 1958; (TS, 3 pages) (Folder 5.47)
    - Monnier, Mathilde. "Printemps,", n.d.; (TS, 8 pages) (Folder 5.48)
    - Zen, Sophia Chen. "Miss E's Trip to China,", 1923-1924; (TS, 5 pages w/pics) (Folder 5.49)
    - Zen, Sophia Chen. "Art of Persuading an Absolute Monarch in Chinese History,", [ca.1952]; (TS 11 pages) (Folder 5.50)
    - Reading Lists, [ca. 1948]; (TS, 11 pages) (Folder 5.51)
    - Unidentified literary works, 1850-1958, n.d.; (3 items) (Folder 5.52)
  - Published Material
    - Dunne, Finley Peter "Mr. Dooley...,", March 13, 1912; (2 TS, 14 pages) (Folder 5.53)
    - "News from Vassar" notices and drafts, 1958; (2 TS, 6 pages) (Folder 5.54)
- SERIES III. PRINTED MATERIALS
  - Addresses and Announcements
    - Faculty statement to President Taylor, [ca. 1913 - 1914]; (TS, 2 pages) (Folder 5.55)
    - Trustees accept resignation of Eloise, [March 1939]; (TS, 1 page) (Folder 5.56)
    - Speech given by Adlai Stevenson, June 7, 1954; (TS, 5 pages) (Folder 5.57)
  - Articles Written by Eloise Ellery
    - Aricles in Current History, 1928-1929; (4 articles) (Folder 6.58)
  - Articles Written about Eloise Ellery
    - Printed picture dedication, Vassarion, 1913; (2 pages) (Folder 6.59)
    - "Eloise Ellery Chair," Alumnae Magazine, Dec. 1958; (1 page) (Folder 6.60)
  - Booklets
    - Guidebook of Geneve, (1 item) (Folder 6.61)
    - Newcomer, Mabel, "You are a Taxpayer,", 1939; (1 item) (Folder 6.62)
    - Thompson, C. Mildred. "Carpet-baggers in U.S. Senate" and "Freedman's Bureau in Georgia,", 1914-1921; (2 items) (Folder 6.63)
    - Miscellaneous: Goodhart's "British Constitution," M.L. King's "Our Struggle," and the 50th Anniversary Security Trust Company, 1942-1956; (3 items) (Folder 6.64)
  - Newspaper Clippings
    - Articles about Eloise Ellery, 1915-1958; (10 articles) (Folder 7.65)
    - Articles about Frank M. Ellery, 1926-1926, n.d.; (21 articles) (Folder 7.66)
    - Articles from Le Figaro, 1952-1953; (3 articles) (Folder 7.67)
    - Ralph McGill Columns, 1952-1953; (3 articles) (Folder 7.68)
    - Articles related to correspondents, 1949-1954, n.d.; (8 articles) (Folder 7.69)
    - Editorials, 1937-1954, n.d.; (13 articles) (Folder 7.70)
    - News articles, 1928-1955; (3 articles) (Folder 7.71)
    - Obituaries, 1920-1958, n.d.; (20 articles) (Folder 7.72)
    - Political cartoons, 1951-1953; (3 cartoons) (Folder 7.73)
    - Book reviews, 1953-1956; (2 articles) (Folder 7.74)
    - Weather reports, [ca. 1924]; (8 articles) (Folder 7.75)
    - Electoral Voting reports, 1920-1928; (6 articles) (Folder 7.76)
    - Miscellaneous, 1870-1954, n.d.; (20 articles) (Folder 7.77)
- SERIES IV. PERSONAL COMMONPLACE BOOKS
  - Eloise Ellery's Daily Diaries
    - Diary of Eloise Ellery, Dec. 25, 1940-Oct. 4, 1941 (Folder 8.78)
    - Diary of Eloise Ellery, Jan. 1, 1942-April 1, 1942 (Folder 8.79)
    - Diary of Eloise Ellery, Jan. 1, 1943-Nov. 24, 1943 (Folder 8.80)
    - Diary of Eloise Ellery, Jan. 1, 1944-Nov. 29, 1944 (Folder 8.81)
    - Diary of Eloise Ellery, Jan. 1, 1945-Dec. 31, 1945 (Folder 8.82)
    - Diary of Eloise Ellery, Jan. 1, 1946-Dec. 31, 1946 (Folder 8.83)
    - Diary of Eloise Ellery, Jan. 1, 1947-Dec. 31, 1947 (Folder 8.84)
    - Diary of Eloise Ellery, Jan. 1, 1948-Dec. 31, 1948 (Folder 9.85)
    - Diary of Eloise Ellery, Jan. 1, 1949-Dec. 28, 1949 (Folder 9.86)
    - Diary of Eloise Ellery, Jan. 1, 1950-Dec. 31, 1950 (Folder 9.87)
    - Diary of Eloise Ellery, Jan. 1, 1951-Dec. 31, 1951 (Folder 9.88)
    - Diary of Eloise Ellery, Jan. 1, 1952-Dec. 31, 1952 (Folder 9.89)
    - Diary of Eloise Ellery, Jan. 1, 1953-Dec. 31, 1953 (Folder 10.90)
    - Diary of Eloise Ellery, Jan. 1, 1954-Dec. 31, 1954 (Folder 10.91)
    - Diary of Eloise Ellery, Jan. 1, 1955-Jan. 1, 1956. (Folder 10.92)
    - Diary of Eloise Ellery, Jan. 1, 1956-Nov. 1, 1956 (Folder 10.93)
    - Diary of Eloise Ellery, Jan. 1, 1957-Dec. 31, 1957 (Folder 10.94)
  - Record Books and Notes
    - Gradebook, 1926-1927 (Folder 11.95)
    - Gradebook, 1948-1939 (Folder 11.96)
    - Personal Health Record, 1953-1955 (Folder 11.97)
    - Journal of Books read and quotations, 1919-1956 (Folder 11.98)
    - Notes from reading I, (116 items) (Folder 12.99)
    - Notes from reading II, (163 items) (Folder 12.100)
    - Notes from reading III, (113 items) (Folder 12.101)
  - Frank M. Ellery's Daily Diaries
    - Diary of Frank Ellery, Jan. 3, 1910-Dec. 31, 1910 (Folder 13.102)
    - Diary of Frank Ellery, Jan. 1, 1920-Dec. 31, 1920 (Folder 13.103)
    - Diary of Frank Ellery, Jan. 1, 1923-Dec. 31, 1923 (Folder 14.104)
    - Diary of Frank Ellery, Jan. 1, 1924-Dec. 31, 1924 (Folder 14.105)
    - Diary of Frank Ellery, Jan. 1, 1928-Dec. 31, 1928 (Folder 15.106)
    - Diary of Frank Ellery, Jan. 1, 1929-Feb. 4, 1929 (Folder 15.107)
    - Items removed from diaries of Frank Ellery, (13 items) (Folder 15.108)
- SERIES V. LEGAL DOCUMENTS
  - Travel Documents
    - Itinerary of world tour, March 27, 1923; (4 pages) (Folder 16.109)
    - Contract for tour, July 17, 1923; (7 pages) (Folder 16.110)
    - Mail instructions while on tour, [1923-1924]; (3 items) (Folder 16.111)
    - Eloise Ellery's passports, 1923-1930; (3 items) (Folder 16.112)
    - Frank Ellery's passport, 1923; (1 item) (Folder 16.113)
  - Letter of Introduction
    - Letter from State Department, April 25, 1908; (1 notice w/seal) (Folder 16.114)
    - Letter from President H.N. MacCracken, June 1, 1939; (1 page) (Folder 16.115)
  - Library Cards
    - Cards from Library of Congress, Bibliotheque Nationale, 1934-1941; (3 cards) (Folder 16.116)
  - Estates
    - Alling, Abby M.: Statement of accounts, [ca. 1929]; (7 pages) (Folder 16.117)
    - Alling, Abby M.: Receipt of assets, March 29, 1929; (2 pages) (Folder 16.118)
    - Ellery, Eloise: Drafts of will, legatees, 1944-1955; (6 items) (Folder 16.119)
    - Ellery, Eloise: Notices to executor, 1939-1955; (2 items) (Folder 16.120)
    - Ellery, Eloise: Estate inventories by Helen D. Lockwood, 1958; (19 items) (Folder 16.121)
    - Frazer, Mary, 1934-1944; (3 items) (Folder 16.122)
  - Oversized
    - Diploma of Mary Alida Alling Rochester Collegiate Institute (Mapcase — Drawer 36)
    - Eloise Ellery Vassar College Diploma, 1897 (Mapcase — Drawer 36)
    - Eloise Ellery Diploma Ph. D. Cornell University (Mapcase — Drawer 36)
    - Eloise Ellery “Medalla de Plata..." from Don Antonio Maura y Montaner (Mapcase — Drawer 36)
    - Frank M. Ellery two (2) certificates of admission to the New York State Bar, 20 June 1879, 13 June 1879 (Mapcase — Drawer 36)
    - Frank M. Ellery Broadside. Union School Number Ten, 10 April 1862; (photocopy) (Mapcase — Drawer 36)
- SERIES VI. FINANCIAL DOCUMENTS
  - Statement of investments, 1947; (2 pages) (Folder 17.123)
  - Carnegie Foundation pension plan, [1930]; (2 pages) (Folder 17.124)
  - Bills and receipts - Eloise Ellery, 1940-1958; (6 items) (Folder 17.125)
  - Bills and receipts - Frank Ellery, 1928; (1 item) (Folder 17.126)
- SERIES VII. THE ELLERY FAMILY
  - Biographical data Eloise Ellery, 1943-1951; (4 pages) (Folder 17.127)
  - Biographical data Frank Ellery, (1 item) (Folder 17.128)
  - Family trees and drafts, (11 items) (Folder 17.129)
  - Geneology of John Sibley I, (20 pages) (Folder 17.130)
  - Geneology of John Sibley II, (22 pages) (Folder 17.131)
- SERIES VIII. PHOTOGRAPHS
  - Photos of Eloise Ellery's family, including Frank Ellery, (14 photos) (Folder 17.132)
  - Photos relating to Rebecca L. Lowrie, (10 photos) (Folder 17.134)
  - Photos of C. Mildred Thompson, (7 photos) (Folder 17.135)
  - Photos of others, (5 photos) (Folder 17.136)
  - Unidenified photos, (9 photos) (Folder 17.137)
- SERIES IX. FRAGMENTS
  - Miscellaneous: war rationbook, folder covers with notations in Eloise Ellery's hand, (7 items) (Folder 17.138)